Guide to the Women Affiliated with Yale University Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Women Affiliated with Yale University records
1956-1989
RU 73
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
The records consist of the constitution, newsletters, membership lists, bank statements, and correspondence documenting Women Affiliated with Yale (formerly the Yale Dames).
Women Affiliated with Yale
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 40 (YRG 40), Records of Yale clubs, societies, and organizations.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the materials is restricted. See Collection Contents for details.
Associated Materials
Yale Dames Records (RU 1065). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by type of material.
Biographical / Historical
In 1926, Mrs. Wilbur Cross, wife of the dean of the graduate school, and Mrs. Robert Corwin, also a faculty wife, began taking an active interest in the group. They were assisted by Mrs. Avery Cross. Meetings were often held in the Cross home and the membership grew substantially. It was at this time that other faculty wives were invited to be sponsors and were soon to add many activities.
In 1930, Professor Edgar Furniss became dean of the graduate school. Dean and Mrs. Furniss became interested in the Dames and made available for their meetings the women's lounge in the graduate school. The organization grew rapidly and was soon had to move its meetings to the faculty lounge.
As a rule, meetings were held in the afternoons followed by tea. Dames prepared the tea and food and faculty wives and sponsored were asked to pour. Many activities were planned, including plays, picnics, and dances. Special interest groups were formed, assuming responsibility for a series of programs in which the members participated. By 1936, evening meetings were held in addition to the afternoon meetings. The high spot of each year's program was the big dinner meeting at which a prominent person was invited to speak. Mrs. Franklin Delano Roosevelt was one such guest.
During the war, as registration dropped, the Dames became a very small organization. It was decided that Dames return to the small home meetings and the sponsor group would disband. Following the war, wives of Yale's undergraduates were invited to join the organization. Teas became large evening meetings with a program in Strathcona auditorium followed by refreshments in the tower where the crowd spilled over into several rooms. Meetings continued to be held in Strathcona hall until 1955 when they returned to the graduate school.
Membership declined in the late 1960s, as the women's movement led many women away from traditionally sex-determined roles. The organization changed its name to Women Affiliated with Yale (WAY) in 1977 and opened its membership to all women connected with the university except undergraduates.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of the constitution, newsletters, membership lists, bank statements, and correspondence documenting Women Affiliated with Yale (formerly the Yale Dames).
College teachers' spouses -- Social networks; Women graduate students; Women -- Education (Higher); Women -- Societies and clubs; Women Affiliated with Yale; Yale University -- Employees -- Societies, etc.; Yale University -- Faculty -- Societies, etc.; Yale University -- Societies, etc.; Yale University. Yale Dames
- Records, circa 1956-1989; Accession 1990-A-142
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted until Jan 1, 2024.
  - Constitution and History, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Newsletter
    - 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Membership Lists and Forms, 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Information for New Members, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Flyers, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and Forms concerning Tax-Exempt Status, 1978-1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Treasurer's Annual Reports, 1960-1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Savings Account Statements, 1971-1987 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Checking Account Statements
    - 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1977-1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Canceled Checks
    - 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Receipts
    - 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - 1980-1985 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Original Stationery and Poster Designs, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Accounts Ledger, 1956-1989 (Box 2, Folder 24)